Hey friends, I've got some really
exciting news for you, which is that we
are launching another channel. This one
with the person who taught me how to be
a journalist, Max Fischer. Back when I
was a lowly animator, finding my way in
this world. Max was a reporter. He had
been a foreign reporter for a decade. He
had a lot to teach me. And I shadowed
him. I wasn't really supposed to be
writing scripts, but I was writing
scripts when I was at Vox. And Max would
edit those scripts and we would make
videos together. Eventually, we invented
the map explainer format together. Iran
steps up its influence in
>> you see this now all the time on my
channel. It's a mainstay of the channel,
but Max was a co-developer of that
format. We then went our separate ways.
I started my own channel here and he
went off to be a columnist at the New
York Times and then to become a
podcaster. He wrote this amazing book
called The Chaos Machine and I actually
read his book and reached out to him and
said, "Hey, uh, we should reconnect."
So, we reconnected and I floated this
idea like what if you came over and
started a channel here at New Press
where we are building creatorled
channels with journalists who care about
explaining things and helping audiences
understand the crazy news environment we
live in. We've been working on that for
about a year now and today it's live.
It's called the bigger picture with Max
Fischer and it will be your guide to
understand the tumultuous news
environment that we live in right now.
not outrage and opinion and
fear-mongering. This is going to be
rigorous reporting that helps you
understand what is happening in the
world. Helps you make sense of it, helps
you aggregate all of the things that are
happening so that you don't feel so
overwhelmed. He's going to publish a lot
more than I publish on my channel
because he's very prolific and much
faster. So, the bigger picture is live
right now. You can see the link in the
description. And if you like what you
see on this channel, you're going to
like what's over there. For those who
are still here, the rest of this video
is going to be a conversation that I had
with Max. We talk about our origin
story. We talk about media. We talk
about a bunch of things. I hope you
enjoy my conversation with Max Fischer,
the newest new press journalist.
>> Max Fischer, welcome to our studio.
>> Hey, pal. First,
I know. I can't believe it. Seen it like
any other viewer. I've seen it so many
times and now I'm here. And let me tell
you, it's even better than you thought
it was. And it's so much tidier. Yeah,
>> I feel like I've shrunk into like a
little shoe box.
>> I almost feel like I need to give people
a warning before they come. Like, come
to the studio. It's not going to It's
not what you think.
>> It feels It's just what you think it's
going to be from the videos. Except one
ate the size. [laughter]
>> We actually crammed into a dollhouse,
right?
>> We are. And we we've taken a weird sense
of pride in like continuing to operate
this like increasingly large media
company.
>> Punishing yourself with this tiny little
studio. Yeah. that works. Like it's
worked, but then it doesn't work. It's
like too small.
>> But like there's something about just
jamming everything into this space that
also is like really
>> spot-on for what we make, which is like
>> it is it feels very warm. It feels very
lived. It feels like this is all stuff
that it feels like I arrived in the
middle of a shoot and like eight
different videos happening in real life.
>> Yeah. And that is kind of what's
happening always. Just stuff.
>> Do you feel like you live inside the
channel at this point?
>> Sometimes I do. This morning I was
driving my son uh from something. We
went rock climbing and he was asking me
about the immune system cuz he was
feeling a little bit sick
>> and I suddenly was in the middle of an
explainer where [laughter] I me and Chad
GBT and him were all like exploring the
deeper understanding of how antibodies
work and how the immune system works
with a viral infection and all these
things and and so sometimes I do think
that my life is a
>> giant explainer because I've I just I'm
always doing to to the point like one
time I was with my my friend on the
streets of San Francisco waiting to get
into a restaurant and I was explaining
to him something about like the Horn of
Africa and pirates and I was like and I
had like my Google maps out and I was
like if you zoom in you'll see here and
the big boats can go past this thing
[laughter] and I literally was
screenshotting it and drawing a line and
then like a fan walked up
>> and and like they just like walked into
like an explainer.
>> So you're just doing the video all the
time all the time. You are just like a
caricature. You should anytime you feel
like someone is like walking around you
and like they're kind of looking like is
that Johnny Harris to get recognized?
You should just start talking about the
horn of Africa just so people think like
yeah that is what I do all the time.
>> All the time.
>> Yeah.
>> All right let's introduce who you are
because you are now uh part of the
family as it were.
>> Reunited.
>> Reunited. This is a this is a very
important reuniting because we were in
the trenches together almost a decade
ago. I know
>> building another new media venture that
was [snorts]
making waves and uh then we went our
separate ways and now we're back doing
it again. So, Max Fischer is a acclaimed
international reporter who has worked at
little newspapers such as the Washington
Post, the New York Times. Um, I know him
from Vox, which is where I got my start
in journalism.
>> I walked into Vox as an animator with no
understanding of what journalism really
was other than it had to do with
newspapers, but I had a lot of
curiosity. I had some animation skills
and I had a degree in international
relations and I got into Vox. It was
2014. Vox was brand spanking new. It was
like this industrial concrete floors
startup millennial vibes everywhere and
all these young smart journalists that
like just sort of threw me into the
trenches and we start I started to learn
how like mass communication worked. and
you were the head of the foreign desk at
Vox. I'm curious first off how you got
started in journalism, but how did you
end up at Vox? Like what was the the
origin story of you getting there? I've
I don't actually know the answer to this
question. I mean, it's funny to hear you
describe
Vox as another kind of like independent
starter cuz at the time it was and at
the time doing like a bunch of people,
it was the Washington Post and like a
bunch of people leaving the Washington
Post like one of the most institutional
establishment media brands you could
have to start a website owned by another
company felt like the most like
independent rebellious thing you could
do. And that feels so quaint now. Like
now that feels like and in some ways is
just like another form of establishment
institutional media. You're just like
working for a different company. But
>> I like a lot of I'm 40 and like a lot of
people my generation like I came up in
college during like the Iraq war and
like it was an era when I thought of
journalism as something that was really
important. But I also thought like
really had my quibbles with like the
mainstream media and thought like the
mainstream media instal media has all
these biases that like help bring about
the Iraq war. But I also that's like the
only only game in town. If you want to
be a journalist and like you want to
help people understand the world because
you think the world is fun and
fascinating and like interesting and
important and it's like a good to help
people understand it. you have to go to
if not a big newspaper than like a news
website that is started by people who
worked at a newspaper and it's crazy to
look back at that now 10 years later and
like the world is so much bigger
>> you know like the things you can do with
the media is so much bigger I know that
doesn't answer your question but they're
like the answer to your question is just
that
>> so fast
>> it changed so fast yes
>> the answer to your question is I just
like I loved helping people around me
understand what was going on especially
at moments when they felt like confused
or like it's upsetting or like I don't
know like when the news is scary or when
things feel like destabilizing. I feel
like there's a specific kind of
journalism that I think you and I ended
up doing like took our different paths
to that you could call explainer
journalism. Although that always feels
like a little pat
gimmicky.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Like the BBC used to have a series
called like explainer and it was like
explainer what's going on in Lebanon
[laughter] and it was like the most
simple like Wikipedia timeline.
>> It was like a Google result.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And and like
that was explainer. It was like a boiled
down like computerenerated but like in
>> and it doesn't it doesn't enlighten you.
>> Yeah. That's I feel like
>> and so what you're describing
>> is an impulse that I have too which is
like a desire to
>> explain but like the deeper thing I
think is like
>> to give people the the full story or at
least a deep a bigger version of the
story that allows whatever the event is
happening right now to make sense in the
context
>> and and therefore the the event right
now the headline that you're hearing
about actually like makes sense and it
sinks in as like a real thing that that
happened and has a has a before.
>> Do you ever read this book Ghost Wars by
Steve Call?
>> Yeah, of course.
>> Great book. That is the book that made
me want to
>> really made me like understand the kind
of work that I wanted to do. Before I
read that, I was like, I want to be in
media, but I'm not really sure what I'm
trying to accomplish with it.
>> Yeah. And for people who don't know,
this is a book about like the entirety
of the history of Afghanistan leading up
to the Taliban, al Qaeda, 9/11, the
American invasion of Afghanistan is
basically like how did all of these
global forces come together for this to
happen. And I remember reading that book
and it talking about like religious
fundamentalists in the Gulf States and
political turmoil in Pakistan and the
Cold War and all of these things that
came together to like put this little
country in the middle of Asia on this
path that ended up being the center of
the world basically and having this
moment of being like
>> I get it now. Like I had been reading
about Afghanistan in the news for years
just like as a news consumer but I
didn't like why is this happening here
like what is the deal with this place
and having this moment of like the
pieces click together
>> and it feels so satis that like aha
moment feels so satisfying and it feels
so empowering
>> and I loved that moment so much. I was
like, I want to do this for other people
like
>> forever basically. And I think that both
because it like it feels really good
>> and it's just I think especially when
people feel like scared or upset about
the world. That's like those are the
moments when I've really thought the
most about like why am I doing this?
What is my purpose here? That I feel
like that's when it's the most
>> important. Yeah. just because it gives
us the tools to understand like what's
happening to us and around us so we feel
like we can navigate it as an
individual. It feels really empowering
>> man. That's cool. That's it's cool to
hear that you had that impulse to like
create this Steve call empowering
>> enlightenment understanding the feeling
of understanding
>> um early on and like you felt it and
then you wanted to to create it. I feel
like my my sort of intuition around this
it also comes from that same thing. It
comes from like a I wish someone had
explained it like this.
>> Totally.
>> So I'm going to construct something in a
way that makes sense for me. And it
turns out that like a lot of people
>> secretly want to understand the world in
that way. And yet,
>> yeah,
>> I always had such a problem with
traditional forms of explaining things
both in school textbooks and in
journalism
>> because it always felt like there was
something I didn't know like like they
like they they say all these words and
they just and there's such a
presumptuous voice.
>> There's a big hole in the middle of the
story.
>> Yeah. And it's like is no one
acknowledging it? It must be a me
problem is what I thought for a lot of
years. It's like, oh, everyone knows
what Sunni and Shia are in terms of like
>> why there's the conflict there. It's
like, I forgot to read that article that
explained that
>> everyone knows though because they're
saying it so nonchalantly that like
everyone must know.
>> And
>> and the truth is they don't know.
>> They don't know. They don't know.
>> It's so funny that you mentioned Sunni
and Chia specifically. That was actually
the moment like the radicalizing moment
for me. I was at the Washington Post.
Syrian civil war was happening and I was
reading all of these stories about like
quoteunquote why it broke out or like
why there are these like fighting
between Sunni and Shia or these
different groups or like why is the
country fissuring along certain lines
and I like would talk to the reporters
too because they were my colleagues who'
be like hey I'm going to write something
about this like it didn't really seem
like you had space to address this or
like what's going on with this religious
conflict and I would realize that they
were incredibly skilled and talented at
this very important work of gathering
facts
>> and like telling me what was going on in
that moment. But that that is a
different set of skills from
understanding deeply
why are things happening the way that
they are like what is the hole in the
middle of the story of like
>> and often didn't even think to ask that
question and like wanting to go out and
be like well like let me actually try to
understand in like a deep way like why
did this country out of all countries
break out into this war
>> out of all wars and it turns out that
there's a good reason that people don't
answer the question right there's a real
explanation also a good reason people
don't answer
It's hard to figure that out.
>> And then it's hard like once you gain
>> to then communicate that to people in a
format that is short and clear and that
a million people can engage with. That's
the then the next difficult thing which
is why I love visuals and why I love
animation because animation is this like
fourth dimension of understanding where
you can use you can use a grid you can
use colors you can use motion you can
use sound and music
>> to teach.
>> Was there a moment that you felt like
you saw that power that visuals had in
storytelling and like explanatory power?
For me, it it started actually when I
was like an elementary school student
really
>> because I'm super dyslexic. Okay.
>> And so reading was always so difficult
for me.
>> Oh.
>> And so I I would go through sort of the
traditional linear forms of learning
which were always
>> based on you know memorizing names and
dates and regions and kind of like it's
a it's a very sort of taxonomy like
labels are the important thing. If you
can remember the labels and you can
repeat the string of words,
>> then that's smart. I was always so bad
at that.
>> I needed to understand it like in my
belly
>> or I wouldn't understand it at all. And
the only way for me to do that was to
visualize it. And so
>> starting really young, I would ask to do
like video projects to like
>> Oh, that's cool.
>> reenact something or to make a video
about it. that the the act of making
something so that I knew someone would
have to watch and understand was was
like that was my the beginning of my
training. I didn't even know it. And
that continued into college. I was
studying
>> IR and a ton of econ like it like it was
basically an econ major. And so I do all
these graphs and all these graphs and I
started to just design the graphs like I
learned I taught myself like um Adobe
Illustrator and started to redesign all
the graphs and try to understand like
why does it slope down like this and
like making it beautiful and and like
>> just expressing it visually was a tool
for me not for anyone else's consumption
other than like my own or or a teacher.
So that was sort of the basis of it and
and
>> so it wasn't even just that you were a
visual learner. was that in order to get
the things that you had in your head
that you knew, you understood for
yourself to convey them to other people.
>> Yes. It had I had to process it through
the nonlinear process of
>> visualizing things and and so in college
I I was I wanted to be in the foreign
service. I wanted to be a diplomat. Like
I was very into like international
things,
>> but I was like always leaning on video
both as like an artistic passion. I
liked the aesthetic of of like being
able to make pictures move and
photograph things.
>> But then when I learned about animation
and graphic design,
>> that helped me unlock curiosity. And
then maps, that's why maps are such a
huge part of my life is because they are
the ultimate like
>> if you want to understand something
visually like a map's a fantastic way
where you actually have
>> people and politics and space that you
can then like draw things on. I feel
like you really unlocked map guy gender
inclusive as an identity for people.
[laughter] Like people were out there
and knew that they loved maps, but I
feel like now people know that like no,
you can be a map guy gender inclusive as
like who you are in your heart. And like
I didn't realize that about myself until
you and I were working together.
>> Are you a map guy?
>> I am now thanks thanks to you. I love
maps. [laughter]
>> So that that brings us to Vox 2015
>> Syrian Civil War once again.
>> Yeah. Um, I was learning how to be a
journalist and kind of being torn apart.
Like to be honest, like I was hired as
an animator. Everyone was whipsmart.
>> I'd never published anything to anyone
other than just like small little things
for think tanks.
>> And I'm like, I want to write scripts
and like report on things. And you all
were like, these scripts are really
thin. And you like taught me how to like
actually beef up scripts. And I was
always good at explaining and
storytelling,
>> right? But I didn't have the like really
make this thing rigorously reported. So
I got a lot of training for you and one
of the big moments like a real
life-changing moment for me was you and
I were both feeling the same impulse
that now I understand was like a thing
that you had felt for many years. Syrian
civil war. What's going on? Everyone's
asking this question now cuz it was 2014
2015. It's like a really coming to a
head in a big way. the news and
>> I can't even think of something that's
happened since then where it was like
everybody was paying attention to it and
everybody was like confused.
>> Yeah. We really wanted to understand it
>> and we were and I think we sent around
on Slack like a New York Times uh
article called like Syrian civil war
colon who is fighting whom and there was
a whom and we just [laughter] like
totally like leaned in to just
on the times for
>> um and we're like this explainer doesn't
do it like let's
>> totally
>> do what they tried to do.
>> It's a list of facts which is not an
explanation. And it's like and it's and
it's like trying to break it down with
like bullet points and it's like let's
actually tell this story in 6 minutes.
>> And so that is when I turned to the map
and started thinking about like these
icons and you started writing an
explanation. And then we like came
together and we we developed this notion
of like what if we could give every one
of the players or the the the groups
their own icon
>> and we can load them up with motivation
and with stakes and put them in
territory
>> and we can summarize what they want and
where they are and the evolution of this
thing in a single take. just a just a
map the entire time and everyone's
moving around on on the on the board
>> and that we we worked on that. It was
probably, you know, 2 3 weeks. You
voiced it
>> which felt like so long.
>> Yeah, it felt like we like 2 3 weeks and
it was 6 minutes long back then. That
was like our longest video. Like no
one's going to watch this.
>> We had to get permission to make it 6
minutes.
>> Yeah. Because we were doing like
two-minute explainers back then.
>> You voiced it like under a blanket or
something cuz we didn't have a VO booth.
So you were just like under a blanket.
You voiced it. I animated it in like a
few days and we put it out and like it
went bananas.
>> 100 million views on on Facebook back
when that was the, you know, pivot to
video.
>> I was just actually thinking about that
moment because, you know, I knew we were
going to have this conversation. I knew
we were going to talk about like, oh,
like how did the arc of my career like
bring us back together again? And I was
thinking about the fact that 10 years
ago when we made that I despite my like
skepticism of the establishment media
had become like you know had spent years
in it and become like kind of a creature
of it. So in my mind my job as a
journalist and the pinnacle of
journalism was writing articles writing
like thousandword articles that people
would read on the internet. And there I
was at Vox writing articles about the
Syrian civil war that would do like by
our standards really well and get like a
hundred thousand reads or maybe even
200,000 reach which was like we couldn't
believe we were reaching that many
people. And then I worked with you and
we made a 6-minute video that reached
tens of millions of people. And I was
like, well, that was a fun experiment,
but I'm going to go back to my real job
now of writing articles, [laughter]
which is obviously like the pinnacle of
the form. And did did that for another
like five or six years before I was
like, huh, that's interesting that I did
one version that reached this many
people and another version that reached
a trillion people more and also it's
more fun to watch and it's more
interesting.
>> I wonder if there's something to that.
>> Wow. I love that. Yeah, you always had
the the sensibility around visuals which
I've recently learned it's because you
are a cinema like
>> I so I have no as as people will learn
quickly I have no technical skills
whatsoever but I do love visual
storytelling and movies especially
because it just uses all the senses. It
engages all of I've never had an art
form before that uses every other art
form in one. It's so cool. It's so cool
and there's so much power in it if you
choose to use it. And I think that's the
big thing that I learned at Vox was
>> most people cuz it was there was a
revolution happening at that time that I
was able to like sort of catch the wave
on
>> which was everyone was like oh digital
video video journalism needs to be
reinvented
>> and most outlets were pouring lots of
money on it but they were just basically
saying like let's make pretty
>> articles like let's make let's like
write articles and then like pretty bold
>> and we were like well what if we engage
all the senses and make sure that the
voice talks to the motion in the
animation which talks to the B-roll
which sets up the evidence for that and
like we actually make it a choreographed
>> experience and that was truly like the
secret to this and that was a Jos Fong
>> like
>> Jos Fong who was one of the founders of
the box video team and my editor there
>> that was her whole thing was like
>> make the voice and the visuals dance
together that's the most effective
version
>> and we that's what we've built this
whole thing off of is is is making
explainers that really tightly like
leverage the power of visuals.
>> Well, and we're at I think a really
exciting moment for that because for the
last hundred years, anything that like
looks good in a movie has been
incredibly expensive to make. Like it
would cost tens of millions of dollars
to make like a good-looking frame that
had interesting effects in it and that
like lighting that looked good. And the
fact that you were able to reproduce
something that would have, you know,
previously required like years of
fundraising to get the money for that
you could do in like a few weeks. Like
>> obviously a huge amount of that is the
skill that you and the team bring to it,
which is like not something you
reproduce. But we're also in a moment
where it's possible for someone like our
size
>> to do something that looks as good as a
lot of movies look
>> and has this special thing which I think
New Press is really built off of which
is it's it is relatable and human and
even though it's it's produced you still
sense that like human flavor. It's like
small enough
>> that that is the ethic of the internet.
Like that is the reprieve that people
once they could express themselves and
consume really conversational relatable
things. We learned that everyone
secretly wanted it.
>> But because of the choke point, the
bottlenecks of corporate like
gatekeepers like
>> no one could actually have access to
that. And so I really believe that like
this next era
needs to continue to push the form and
especially with AI like the amount of
like visual craziness that we'll be able
to do is just going to explode even
more.
>> But
>> how do we do that while also maintaining
this beautiful thing that like someone
watches and says like, "Oh, that's a
real person with real questions. they're
earnest
>> and I can relate to them
>> and and therefore like I trust them and
I want to be a part of their inquiry.
That's a really important ingredient for
me
>> and it's something that I mean it
obviously has its roots in kind of like
>> 2000's era blogging and 2010s era
blogging where you feel like and I think
that also is it's been forgotten because
it was so long ago now. But I think a
lot of that too is like a reaction to
the Iraq war and the financial crisis
and a sense of like these big
institutional outlets like I'm not sure
I can trust them happening at the same
time as the internet. Now I can access
someone who is, you know, even if it's
just whoever, just a blogger on their
site, feels like a real person who's
like, they might not be perfect, but
they're walking me through what they're
thinking. They're being transparent
about it. They're not doing this
institutional authority voice from
nowhere, view from nowhere kind of
thing. And I mean, I think when I think
about like the first vloggers to really
capture that, like Hank Green, you know,
>> it's someone who you just you feel like
you trust them immediately because
they're bringing you along on this
journey. It's like they don't
necessarily have the same resource as a
huge institution. I do feel like we're
at a point where
>> that kind of like the vlogger voice and
the independent voice is something that
it's part of the ecosystem now, right?
Like we all kind of get it. We all know
what it is. It's part of all of our
media diets. But I think we are also all
feeling some kind of a need for
not the institutional weight of a big
media brand but the sense that like I
can really trust
>> what this person outlet newspaper
whatever it is is saying because it
feels really high stakes right now and
it feels really important in a way that
maybe it didn't you know 10 years ago
>> and I think there is a an industry of
professional
artificial
um authenticity that has been created
like the influencer economy has
developed so well where now people can
>> if authenticity was a currency of trust
with the early vloggers and bloggers
>> um then it became effectively kind of
like easy to fake
>> and now people can't trust authenticity
authenticity is now authenticity so
>> and yet I believe especially in a world
of AI that like the humanity of
journalism
>> or the of of of curiosity should always
will always should always shine through
and so there needs to be a balance of
institutional credibility and human
authenticity and that I think new press
like
>> new press is create it's like two sides
of it's it is creator driven meaning the
reason why we have Sam's channel
Kristoff's channel and the channel that
you're launching is creator driven
because
>> we do believe that like the journalism
will be better if it's driven by your
curiosity and people will relate to it.
>> But then we the reason we're tied
together under this umbrella called new
press is because we want that to also
signal trust and say like hey we are
very transparent about the fact that
we're trying to do something really
rigorous here. You can trust us and
we'll earn that trust. We'll earn it.
But then if if you trust new press
because you've spent a lot of time with
me or with Sam, people will hopefully do
like that's what brands are good for is
reducing uncertainty. So they'll look at
your channel and they'll be like, "Okay,
if he's the fourth channel in this thing
and I've trusted the other three,
>> my uncertainties, you don't have to
spend a year like sort of producing that
trust."
>> And I think that that is the power and
the thing that people want is like to be
able to offload some of that uncertainty
to a brand. But the brands that have
that are kind of like or had that
traditionally are now like they they
aren't trusted. And so like we we have
to build that up again. You know what
excites me about this moment in media
amid all of the, you know, economic and
industry trends that are scary, is that
I feel like it's a moment where
audiences really want to come along for
the human element of it. And they want
to come along for exploring the news,
for what it means on a human level. They
want the authenticity of a relationship
with the creator, with the person that
they're following. But they also really
want to come along with the rigor of h
how do we know what we know
>> and why do we why do we think this?
Yeah.
>> You know, what led us to believe this
piece of information? And there's a
sense of,
you know, maybe it's it's years of, I
think, being on social media and seeing
the way that like the Arab Spring
unfolded and seeing that you can follow
along a story in real time in the
internet to understand what's happening,
but also knowing that social media as a
decentralized mass really can't always
be trusted and the algorithms will lead
you in weird directions and who knows
what that thing was that went viral that
I saw. And I think there's a
trust, who I have a human relationship,
who will walk me through what's
happening, and I want to come along on
that journey, and I want to be engaged
in it. And I think that that is a really
unique moment, honestly, in people's
relationship to media.
>> Yeah, it's it's exciting, and we're
going to figure out if it if it works
for the next few years. [laughter] Like,
we'll see. So, let's get to your show
cuz I do want to hear about like how
that fits into like our bundle of
different shows at New Press and like
how you're thinking about it in the
context of this conversation. Um, you
went from Vox to the New York Times. I
remember we went to some restaurant and
you told me you're going to the New York
Times and you were like, I'm leaving.
And I was like, oh Um, and then
you wrote a book, The Chaos Machine,
which is an amazing deep dive into the
rise of algorithms.
>> I loved that book. Um, you have been at
Crooked doing a couple of podcast shows
>> and now you're here. You were launching
a show. The show is called The Bigger
Picture with Max Fischer
>> and it is conceived by you as as like
the new press ethos is is like it's a
creator-driven thing. I want to hear now
that I understand a little bit about
like your your heritage in the curiosity
and explainer stuff, why this show and
what what like what is this going to be
in terms of your expression of like all
of your experience now and what you want
to see in media right now? [snorts]
>> I mean, look, the truth is it's a scary
time. It is a scary time in our world. I
don't think that that's a partisan
statement. And I think that if you look
at like opinion polls, that's an opinion
that people hold truly across the
spectrum. I find reading the news
distressing. I also feel like I have to
read the news because you have to know
what's going on. You have to understand
what's happening. And I hate feeling
caught in that. I hate feeling like I
have to keep up with what's happening
because maybe it's going to burst
through the door tomorrow. But it's
also, you know, it upsets me. It
confuses me. I don't understand where
our world is going, where this country
is going.
And partly his response to that and
feeling like, you know, I spent the last
few years because I kind of I got
disaffected being the mainstream media.
It's also was just like again it's
distressing to read the newspaper all
the time. I thought I want to have more
of a relationship with my readers,
listeners, viewers, whatever. And that
was why I turned to podcasting because
it's more human relationship was during
the pandemic. It was a time we were all
feeling isolated. does feel like it's a
time when
just in order to like get through the
day, we need to understand what's going
on in the world around us. So, that was
a lot of what made it feel appealing and
kind of important to me to have a show
that would the idea is we'll ask a
question with every episode, something
that feels urgent that's, you know,
happening in the world. Why is it so
hard to get a job right now? Why do
people in ICE wear masks? Why is housing
so expensive? Why is my electricity bill
going up? Not all of it's going to be
bad. It's also going to be where I want
to do one on um why does dating feel so
weird now or like why do I hate dating
all of a sudden? Um and then try to
answer those questions in a way that
will
>> take people on a journey
>> and feel surprising. And the idea in the
name of the show, the bigger picture is
that we'll start with some question that
will be about something discreet. Why
are people in ice wearing masks? And
then following that journey, we will
start to see how it connects to all of
these different things that maybe we're
also curious about or maybe we haven't
even thought about about how the law is
changing, about what's going on with
immigration, about, you know, what is
Donald Trump up to. And the idea is that
it will be a journey that is visually
interesting, that is fun to go along on
or at least engage to go along on um
that will have twists and turns and that
at the end of it, you will feel a better
sense of like I get it. I have a sense
of agency over what's happening. I feel
a better sense of like being able to
navigate this world because I have like
a sense for what's going on and why.
Also, a lot of it was just like you were
saying, I'm a big movie guy. I love
visual storytelling. I never thought
that I would have the opportunity to do
primarily visual storytelling because I
don't have those technical skills.
>> So, it felt like absolute serendipity
when you reached out to me. I don't
know, it was a year ago at this point,
something like that. and we're like,
"We're doing this thing. We'd love to
have you come along." Like, I never even
would have entertained
>> the possibility, but getting to plug in
>> to your team, which does such like
incredible work,
>> is really exciting. And the idea of
getting to find ways to tell these
stories that will feel like surprising
and interesting to people.
>> Cool. I love that. That was that's
really fun to hear. And I can't wait to
see the show take off. It's a cool thing
to be at the company like to lead the
company that is producing this show.
>> But because it's led by you, it is your
thing. Like your cinematic inspirations
>> are making it into the art direction.
>> I love being also an audience member.
Like I love like witnessing it come to
life and also helping it and like
supporting it where I can. But like
that's what I feel about Kristoff's
show, Sam's show. Like it it is fun to
be surrounded by other people who are
doing this work. And what I find is that
each of us have our own way of answering
questions. And the answer to the
question is cool.
>> Mhm.
>> But it's actually the journey the like
everyone has their curious little like
way of processing information that
actually is the juicier. Like Sam's
diagrammatic approach to
>> to geopolitics and to like sports is a
way that I don't think I don't think
like that and his curiosity expresses
differently than Kristoff's which is
expresses differently than yours.
>> And so I think that journey thing as a
viewer, as like a consumer, I deeply
value being able to like see how your
brain paths process things and doing
that out loud. It imbuss trust, but it
also
>> makes me process questions differently.
>> Yeah. And and that's what I'm excited
about with this show is like seeing you
do that out loud.
>> Can I tease one of the episodes to speak
to that? So, I'm not going to give away
what the episode is about, but just the
way that it is going to start is
actually a reflection of something that
would like actually happen to me cuz I
wanted to reproduce part of the
experience of be discovering this thing.
I was looking at pictures of the
skylines of different cities. these
skylines of these like Asian mega
cities, you know, Beijing, Shanghai,
Koala Lumpur. I was looking at how new
they looked.
>> And then I looked at a bunch of
different skylines over time, like
photos of like Ryu de Janeiro or Mexico
City going back like 50 years. And if
you look at it, like every 10 years, the
skyline looks different. Like you see it
growing, you see it getting taller, the
buildings look new, it expands outward.
And then I looked at the skylines of
American cities and they did the same
thing up until like 1960 and then they
just stopped. It's completely frozen
place. And it's crazy because you can
see that there was a time when they were
like growing really quickly. And it's
not like these are like
>> some forgotten oldw world cities. Like
these are like New York, Chicago. These
are really vibrant growing cities. But
the and if you look at the sky now,
you'll be like, "Oh wait, all of these
buildings are like from the 1890s.
that's frozen in time. And that was and
I won't give away what the video is
about. But that was something that like
unlocked for me a question that I had
been like kind of it's like one of the
20, you know, how you're always like
researching 20 different things and like
maybe it yields something or maybe it
doesn't. That's when I was like this is
the answer to a question I have been
asking for myself for a while. And I'm
really excited to show people me going
on that journey and like not just see
the different skylines, but like how
that led me to a fun or like an
interesting realization about things
that affect all of us. And you can do
that because the channel is your the
canvas of your own curiosity. And and
like our whole theory with this
different media model is that like
instead of the brand being number one
and all of the voices under the brand
having to conform with the brand's
>> guidelines like a normal sort of
assignment based model,
>> we're flipping that into a place where
the creator's
voice is the number one thing and that
the brand guidelines are there and
they're present and there's standards,
>> but they are not they don't impose
stylistic structures and and so that you
can have your skyline moment
>> and I can have my like whatever going
looking for bunkers in the Swiss Alps
like
>> with Doritos
>> with Doritos and chopsticks to eat my
Doritos because [laughter] you know I
can't get that dust on my fingers.
>> So it's just like our quirky minds
>> do much better work when I I believe
when they can explore at least they they
do work of the kind that you mentioned
which is
>> the explanatory trying to process
information. I think the factbased going
out gathering the facts that is
something that the traditional
institutions do they have bureaus all
over the world they can do that it's so
valuable I never want to like undermine
that our work is made possible because
of that
>> but for the work that I think the world
needs a lot more of curiosity and
understanding
>> I believe that it's best done in a world
where you can nerd out about skylines
>> let me ask you something you are very
much the person you present yourself to
be in your videos like you Are you are
the Johnny Harris? YouTube is like also
the real Johnny Harris. Is that
>> is that something you have to make an
effort to do? Do you know what I mean?
Are you thinking about like how do I
communicate who I am? No.
>> Through this or it just happens.
>> No, no, no. It's it the moment even at
Vox I was able to be kind of my weird
wild self like they let me and that's
the reason I was able to thrive um there
because they let me. It's why when the
New York Times tried to hire me after
that Civil War video, I was like, "No,
like I it's the New York Times, but I I
would be stifled. Like, I wouldn't be
able to do my thing because it for me, I
don't know how to do it any other way."
>> And I tried to pull for that and tried
to like help push along cuz I thought it
would have been so exciting to work
together again, but man, you made the
right choice.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And for me, it was not even
it wasn't even an option because I've
always needed to be able to process in
kind of a nonlinear chaotic way. Yeah.
that was really it was really hard to
conform to anything else. So yeah, this
is me.
>> Um I'm obviously like a you know like a
version of myself on camera that that is
not the full me, but it is a big part of
who I am
>> in terms of a kind of chaotic and very
curious person who doesn't like to
>> do the same thing twice or in the same
way. I like to do it differently every
time. And the fact that YouTube exists
to allow me to do that and to like then
matchmake make me to to to people who
want to watch that like that's a
beautiful thing. It's like the theory of
why I'm able to do this work at all.
Otherwise like
>> I this is this would not be my job. I
wouldn't be able to do this job if I was
born in like the 60s or something.
>> I It's true. [laughter] Yeah. I would
never
I had serpidations about going onto
YouTube. It's like you know I've written
on reported on the company and people
can see what I have said about it. Um
the fact that you are able to do what
you're doing on it I think is the thing
that like gives me faith that like
>> okay it's like you've got the algorithm
and that's you know there's always
there's always a boss you know when I
was working for a newspaper there were
bosses of the newspaper and it's like
now the boss is the algorithm
>> and that's always a set of constraints
that you have to work in right like
that's not a conspiracy theory um
>> but the fact that you were able to do it
and it's like can see it it's rigor it's
real journalism it's rigorous
>> journalism people want And when we do
videos, people show up. Like there is a
lot of people who want this and the
algorithm is effectively a reflection of
human psychology like for better or
worse. But like it does give people what
they want to see. And if people want
there there are a lot of people it turns
out who want rigorous deep explanations
of what is happening in the world
>> and that gives me a lot of hope. It
gives me a lot of hope and it gives me a
lot of hope that this platform that's
that's off the algorithm track can be a
space where we can bring like the people
who want to do that in a big way over to
have even more intimate and like
beautiful learning experiences because
they're out there and they're thirsty
for this
>> and and that gives me a lot of hope even
in spite of all of the polarizing
realities of
>> people are sick of it. people are sick
of I mean there you know there will
always be like intense partisans
whatever but I really think that
>> as much as these so many of these huge
platforms are priming people for like
ultraartisanship and tribalism and
conspiracy theories distrust like I
nobody likes that you know
>> we're get tired of like the outrage
button always being pressed
>> absolutely yeah and I think that like
and look I'm susceptible to it too I'm
not going to claim that I'm immune to it
but like
>> nobody feels good after that and like
you feel good and nourished after
something that feels like
>> enriching and informative.
>> Yeah, totally. Max Fisher is launching
the bigger picture now. I'm very excited
to have you in the family and back
together and we're going to build this
thing together and um I'm I'm rooting
for your channel and here to support it.
>> I am absolutely terrified. This is a a
big a big jump but um I'm really
excited.
>> Cool. and I'm very grateful to be here.
And thank you everyone watching as
supporters of New Press. Um, let us know
what you want more of, like to hear
about, what questions you have. Uh, we
deeply appreciate your support and we
will see you in the next one. [snorts]
That's a that's a wrap.
>> Great. Sign up.